[{"question":"<p><b>Each 325mg tablet of aspirin consists of 195.0mg carbon, 14.6mg hydrogen and 115.4mg oxygen.<\/b><\/p><p><b>Determine its empirical formula (C = 12, H = 1, O = 16).<\/b><\/p>","options":["C<sub>8<\/sub>H<sub>9<\/sub>O<sub>4<\/sub>","C<sub>9<\/sub>H<sub>8<\/sub>O<sub>4<\/sub>","C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>2<\/sub>O","C<sub>9<\/sub>H<sub>4<\/sub>O<sub>8<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Zinc oxide is a<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["basic oxide","acidic oxide","amphoteric oxide","neutral oxide"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>The periodic classification of elements is an arrangement of the elements in order of their<br><\/b><\/p>","options":["atomic weights","isotopic weights","molecular weights","atomic numbers"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>A small quantity of solid ammonium chloride (NH<sub>4<\/sub>Cl) was heated gently in a test tube, the solid gradually disappears to produce two gases. Later, a white cloudy deposit was observed on the cooler part of the test tube. The ammonium chloride is said to have undergone<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["distillation","sublimation","precipitation","evaporation"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>A volume of 42.5ml 0.125M KOH is needed to neutralize completely 37.2ml of H<sub>3<\/sub>PO<sub>4<\/sub> solution. Find the molar concentration of H<sub>3<\/sub>PO<sub>4<\/sub>.<\/b><\/p>","options":["0.480M","0.068M","0.048M","0.084M"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>The number of dissolved particles in solution does not depend on one of the following<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["strong electrolyte","weak electrolyte","non-electrolyte","oxidation number"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>For a 0.262m solution of maltose in water, calculate the freezing point of the solution.\r\nK<sub>f<\/sub> = 1.855\u00b0C; K<sub>b<\/sub> = 0.512\u00b0Cm<sup>-1<\/sup><\/b><\/p>","options":["-0.686\u00b0C","0.456\u00b0C","-0.886\u00b0C","-0.486\u00b0C"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>For a 0.222m solution of sucrose in water, calculate the boiling of the solution. K<sub>b<\/sub> = 0.512\u00b0Cm<sup>-1<\/sup>; K<sub>f<\/sub> = 1.855\u00b0C<sup>-1<\/sup>.<\/b><\/p>","options":["100\u00b0Cm<sup>-1<\/sup>","100.114\u00b0C","99.89\u00b0C","123.5\u00b0Cm<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>An element X forms the following compounds with chlorine XCl<sub>4<\/sub>, XCl<sub>3<\/sub>, XCl<sub>2<\/sub>. This illustrates the<\/b><\/p>","options":["Law of multiple proportion","Law of chemical proportions","Law of simple proportions","Law of conservation of mass"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>When air which contains the gases oxygen, nitrogen, carbondioxide, water vapour and the rare gases, is passed through alkaline pyrogallol and then over quicklime, the only gases left are;<\/b><\/p>","options":["Nitrogen and carbondioxide","The rare gases","Nitrogen and oxygen","Nitrogen and the rare gases"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>When large hydrocarbon molecules are heated at high temperature in the presence of a catalyst to give smaller molecules, the process is known as<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["disintegration","polymerization","cracking","degradation"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>When each of the nitrates of potassium, magnesium and iron is heated,<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["all the nitrates dissolve to their oxides","the nitrate of magnesium gives the nitrite and oxygen","the nitrates of magnesium and iron give the oxides","the nitrate of iron gives the nitrite and oxygen"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>A sample of hard water contains some calcium sulphate and calcium hydrogen carbonate.<\/b><\/p><p><b>The total hardness may therefore be removed by<\/b><\/p>","options":["Boiling the water","Adding excess calcium hydroxide","Adding a calculated amount of calcium hydroxide","Adding sodium carbonate"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>What process would coal undergo to give coal gas, coal tar, ammoniacal liquor and coke?<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["steam distillation","destructive distillation","liquefication","hydrolysis"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Detergents have the general formula _____<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["R(CH<sub>2<\/sub>)<sub>n<\/sub>OH","RSO<sub>3<\/sub><sup>-<\/sup>Na<sup>+<\/sup>","RCO<sub>2-<\/sub>Na+","RCO<sub>2<\/sub>H"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>The formula of the compound formed in a reaction between a trivalent metal M and a tetravalent non-metal X is ____<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["MX","M<sub>3<\/sub>X<sub>4<\/sub>","M<sub>4<\/sub>X<sub>3<\/sub>","M<sub>3<\/sub>X<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>2.25g of a sample of an oxide of copper on reduction gave 2.0g of copper. 2.50g of another oxide of copper on reduction also gave 2.0g of copper. These results are in accordance with the law of __.<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["constant (or definite) proportion","indefinite proportion","multiple proportions","conservation of matter"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>One mole of propane is mixed with five moles of oxygen. The mixture is ignited and the propane burns completely. What is the volume of the product at s.t.p? [G.M.V = 22.4dm<sup>3<\/sup>mol<sup>-1<\/sup>]<\/b><\/p>","options":["112.0dm<sup>3<\/sup>","67.2dm<sup>3<\/sup>","56.0dm<sup>3<\/sup>","44.8dm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>The rate of a reaction is proportional to the number of effective collisions occurring per seconds within the reactants. This statement is associated with the<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["kinetic theory","rate law","gas law","collision law."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>A zero order reaction is one<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["In which the reaction rate does not depend on the concentration of the reactants","In which the reaction rate depends on the concentration of the reactants","In which the rate depends on the temperature of the reaction mixture","All of the above"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Which of the following physical properties decreases across the periodic table?<br><\/b><\/p>","options":["ionization potential","electron affinity","electronegativity","atomic radius"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>What are the possible oxidation numbers for an element if its atomic number is 17?<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["-1 and 7","-1 and 6","-3 and 5","-2 and 6"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>The energy change accompanying the addition of an electron to a gaseous atom is called?<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["first ionization energy","second ionization energy","electron affinity","electronegativity"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>The reaction between an organic acid and an alcohol in the presence of an acid catalyst s known as<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["saponification","dehydration","esterification","hydrolysis"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>If 30cm<sup>3<\/sup> of oxygen diffuses through a porous pot in 7 seconds, how long will it take 60cm<sup>3<\/sup> of chlorine to diffuse through the same pot, if the vapor densities of oxygen and chlorine are 16 and 36 respectively?<\/b><\/p>","options":["9.3 secs","14 secs","21 secs","30.3 secs"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>The electronic configuration of the specie underlined as in the molecule H<sub>2<\/sub><u>S<\/u> is<\/b><\/p>","options":["1s<sup>2<\/sup>2s<sup>2<\/sup>2p<sup>6<\/sup>3s<sup>2<\/sup>3p<sup>6<\/sup>3d<sup>10<\/sup>4s<sup>2<\/sup>4p<sup>4<\/sup>","1s<sup>2<\/sup>2s<sup>2<\/sup>2p<sup>6<\/sup>3s<sup>2<\/sup>3p<sup>4<\/sup>","1s<sup>2<\/sup>2s<sup>2<\/sup>2p<sup>6<\/sup>3s<sup>2<\/sup>3p<sup>2<\/sup>","1s<sup>2<\/sup>2s<sup>2<\/sup>2p<sup>6<\/sup>3s<sup>2<\/sup>3p<sup>6<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>The functional group(s) of an amino acid is\/are ___.<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["NH<sub>2<\/sub>, -COOH","C<sub>n<\/sub>H<sub>2n+1<\/sub>, -COOH","\u2013COCl, COOH","COOH, CONH<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>A student while trying to identify two gases labeled A and B, found that gas A is acidic to litmus paper and turn acidified potassium dichromate solution green, while gas B turns red litmus paper blue and forms dense white fume with hydrogen chloride. The correct identity of A and B respectively are<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["CO<sub>2<\/sub> and N<sub>2<\/sub>","SO<sub>2<\/sub> and NH<sub>3<\/sub>","HCl and NH<sub>3<\/sub>","NO<sub>2<\/sub> and PCl<sub>5<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Which of the following titrations will have a solution with a pH greater than 7 at the end point (equivalence point) of the titration?<\/b><\/p>","options":["Titration of sodium hydroxide with tetraoxosulphate (VI) acid","Titration of sodium trioxocarbonate (IV) with hydrochloric acid","Titration of sodium hydroxide with oxalic acid (ethanedoic acid)","Titration of ammonium hydroxide and trioxonitrate (V) acid"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>9.0dm<sup>3<\/sup> 0f a gas at s.t.p was subjected by means of a movable piston to two times the original pressure with the temperature being now at 364K. What is the volume of the gas in dm<sup>3<\/sup> at this pressure?<\/b><\/p>","options":["2.0","4.5","6.0","8.3"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>An increase in the temperature causes an increase in the pressure of a gas because there is an increase in the<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["average velocity of the molecules","number of collisions between the molecules","free mean path between each molecules and other","none of the above"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>The forces holding naphthalene crystals together can be overcome when naphthalene is heated to a temperature of 354K resulting in the crystals melting. These forces are known as ___.<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["coulombic","ionic","covalent","Van Der Waals"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>A metallic ion X<sup>2+<\/sup> with an inert gas structure contains 18 electrons. How many protons are there in this ion?<\/b><\/p>","options":["20","18","16","2"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>The dependence of rate reaction on temperature is given by<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["Le Chaterlier\u2019s equation","Law of mass action","Arrchenius equation","Rate equation"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<b>Which of the following gases may not be dried with concentrated sulphuric acid?<\/b>","options":["HCl","N<sub>2<\/sub>","Cl<sub>2<\/sub>","NH<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Metal salts of long-chain fatty acids are known as<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["detergents","double salts","soaps","grease"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Cellulose and starch can be classified as one of the following:<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["hydrocarbons","sugars","carbohydrates","alkaloids"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Which of the following in NOT a redox reaction?<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["2HNO<sub>2<\/sub> + 2HI \u2192 2H<sub>2<\/sub>O + 2NO + I<sub>2<\/sub>","Zn + H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> \u2192 ZnSO<sub>4<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>","Ca(HCO<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>2<\/sub> \u2192  CaCO<sub>3<\/sub>  + H<sub>2<\/sub>O + CO<sub>2<\/sub>","4FeO + O<sub>2<\/sub> \u2192 2Fe<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Which of the following processes leads to increase in entropy?<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["mixing of a sample of NaCl and sand","condensation of water vapour","boiling of a sample of water","cooling a saturated solution"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Which of the following statements is true?<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["most solids have low densities","most gases are ionic compounds","solids, like liquids and gases, do not have fixed shapes and fixed volumes","gases do not have their own shape but rather expand to fill the shapes of their containers uniformly"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>A liquid begins to boil when<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["Its volume is slightly decreased","Its vapour pressure is lower than the external pressure","Its vapour pressure equals the external pressure","Its molecules start escaping from the surface"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>An element which exists in more than crystalline form is said to exhibit<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["polymorphism","isotopy","allotropy","isomerism"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>A mixture of starch solution and potassium oxide was placed in a test tube. On adding dilute tetraoxosulphate (VI) acid then K<sub>2<\/sub>Cr<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>7<\/sub> solutions, a blue-black colour was produced. In this reaction, the<\/b><\/p>","options":["iodide is oxidized","tetraoxosulphate (VI) acid acts as an oxidizing agent","starch has been oxidized","K<sub>2<\/sub>Cr<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>7<\/sub> is oxidized"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Which of the following statements is true?<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["The heat of solution of NaOH is positive?","The NaOH gains heat from the surrounding","The heat of solution of NaOH is negative","The dissolution of NaOH in water is endothermic"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Which property of a reversible reaction is affected by a catalyst?<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["heat content (enthalpy)","energy activation","free energy change","equilibrium position"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Which of the following is used in fire extinguishers?<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["carbon (ii) oxide","carbon (iv) oxide","sulphur (iv) oxide","ammonia"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>When H<sub>2<\/sub>S gas is passed into a solution of iron (iii) chloride, the colour changes from yellow to green.<\/b><\/p><p><b>This is because<\/b><\/p>","options":["H<sub>2<\/sub>S is reduced to S","Fe<sup>3+<\/sup> ions are oxidized by H<sub>2<\/sub>S","Fe<sup>3+<\/sup> ions are oxidized by Fe<sup>2+<\/sup> ions","Fe<sup>3+<\/sup> ions are reduced to Fe<sup>2+<\/sup> ions"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Suitable reagents for the laboratory preparation of nitrogen are _____<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["sodium dioxonitrate (III) and ammonium chloride","sodium trioxonitrate (V) and ammonium chloride","sodium chloride and ammonium trioxonitrate (V)","sodium chloride and ammonium diozonitrate"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>The thermal decomposition of copper (II) trioxonitrate (V) yields copper (II) oxide, oxygen and _____<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["nitrogen (II) oxide","nitrogen (I) oxide","nitrogen (IV) oxide","nitrogen"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Which of the following is an example of a chemical change?<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["freezing of water","dissolution of NaCl","rusting of iron","separation a liquid mixture by distillation"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Which of the following is not a member of the homologous series of paraffins (alkanes)?<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["C<sub>3<\/sub>H<sub>8<\/sub>","C<sub>5<\/sub>H<sub>12<\/sub>","C<sub>7<\/sub>H<sub>16<\/sub>","C<sub>24<\/sub>H<sub>48<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Which of the following statement is an exception in the assumptions of the kinetic theory of gases?<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["total kinetic energy of the particles is proportional to the absolute temperature","The particles are in constant random motion","The particles are of negligible mass","The particles collide with each other"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>An example of alcohol is<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["CCl<sub>4<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub>COOH","CHCl<sub>3<\/sub>","CH<Sub>3<\/sub>OH"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Hypochlorous acid is used as a bleach because<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["It is a strong acid","It yields chlorine readily in pure water","It is an oxidizing agent","It is a weak acid"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Which of the following compounds will form a solution if exposed to air?<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["Na<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>3<\/sub>.10H<sub>2<\/sub>O","NaNO<sub>3<\/sub>","CuSO<sub>4<\/sub>","CaCl<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Consider the following exothermic reaction<\/b><\/p><p><b>2SO<sub>2(g)<\/sub> + O<sub>2(g)<\/sub> \u2194 2SO<sub>3(g)<\/sub><\/b><\/p><p><b>If the temperature of the reaction is reduced from 800<sup>0<\/sup>C to 500<sup>0<\/sup>C, and no other change takes place, then<\/b><\/p>","options":["the reaction rate increases","concentration of SO<sub>3<\/sub> decreases","concentration of SO<sub>3<\/sub> increases","O<sub>3<\/sub> gas becomes unreactive"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Alkanoates are formed by the reaction of alkanoic acid with _____<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["alkyl halides","alkanols","ethers","sodium"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Methylethanoate reacts with ammonia to yield ______<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["methylamine and ethanol","ethylamine methanol","methanamide and ethanol","ethanamide and methanol"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Crude copper can be purified by the electrolysis of CuSO<sub>4<\/sub> if<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["Platinum electrodes are used","The crude copper is made the anode of the cell","The crude copper is made the cathode of the cell","Crude copper are used"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Aluminum is extracted commercially from its ore by<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["Heating aluminium oxide with coke in a furnace","The electrolysis of fused aluminium oxide in cryolite","Treating cryolite with sodium hydroxide solution under pressure","Heating sodium aluminium silicate to a high temperature"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Which of the following is used in the manufacture of glass?<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["sodium chloride","sodium trioxocarbonate","sodium tetraoxosulphate (VI)","sodium trioxonitrate (V)"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Three solutions contain carbonate, sulphate and sulphide ions respectively. One test that will identify just ONE of them completely is by addition to each of them of<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["barium chloride solution","dilute hydrochloric acid","lead nitrate solution","calcium chloride solution"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>The following equation H<sub>2<\/sub>O + 2Fe<sup>2+<\/sup> + Cl<sub>2<\/sub> \u2194 2Fe<sup>3+<\/sup> + 2Cl<sup>-<\/sup> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O\r\n<\/b><\/p><p><b>The only ion which behaves as an oxidizing agent is<\/b><\/p>","options":["Fe<sup>2+<\/sup>","Cl<sub>2<\/sub>","Fe<sup>3+<\/sup>","Cl<sup>-<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Which of the following changes is physical?<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["adding iron filling to water","adding sodium metal to aerated water","cooling a solution of iron (II) sulphate to obtain the hydrated salt","Cooling water to obtain ice"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>In titration involving sodium hydroxide and dilute hydrochloric acid, where would you place the base?<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["In the beaker","In the conical flask","In a burette","In the standard flask"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>You are provided with five jars containing SO<sub>2<\/sub>, CO<sub>2<\/sub>, H<sub>2<\/sub>, CO and NO respectively. Select a test from A to E which will identify ANY ONE of the gases completely.<\/b><\/p>","options":["pass each gas into lime water","pass each gas into water and test with litmus","pass each gas into concentrated sulphuric acid","expose each gas to atmospheric air"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>200cm<sup>3<\/sup> each of 0.1M solutions of lead (II) trioxonitrate (V) and hydrochloric acid were mixed. Assuming that lead (II) chloride is completely insoluble, calculate the mass of lead (II) chloride that will be precipitated. [Pb = 207, Cl = 35, N = 14, O = 16]<\/b><\/p>","options":["2.78g","5.56g","8.34g","11.12g"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Which of the following gases will diffuse fastest when passed through a porous plug?<\/b><\/p><p><b>[H = 1, C = 12, N = 14, O = 16]<\/b><\/p>","options":["propane","oxygen","methane","ammonia"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Which of the following will have its mass increased when heated with air?<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["helium","magnesium","copper pyrites","glass"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>A gaseous metallic chloride MCl<sub>x<\/sub> consists of 20.22% of M by mass. The formula of the chloride is [M = 27, Cl = 35.5]<\/b><\/p>","options":["MCl","MCl<sub>2<\/sub>","MCl<sub>3<\/sub>","M<sub>2<\/sub>Cl<sub>6<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>The method that can be used to convert hard water to soft water is<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["chlorination","passage over activated charcoal","the use of an ion-exchange resin","aeration"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Given that electronegativity increases across a period and decreases down a group in the periodic table, in which of the following compounds will the molecules be held together by the strongest hydrogen bond?<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["HF<sub>(g)<\/sub>","NH<sub>3(g)<\/sub>","CH<sub>4(g)<\/sub>","HCl<sub>(g)<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>The correct order of increasing oxidation number of the transition metal ions for the compounds K<sub>2<\/sub>Cr<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>7<\/sub>, V<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>5<\/sub> and KMnO<sub>4<\/sub> is<\/b><\/p>","options":["V<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>5<\/sub> < K<sub>2<\/sub>Cr<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>7<\/sub> < KMnO<sub>4<\/sub>","K<sub>2<\/sub>Cr<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>7<\/sub> < KMnO<sub>4<\/sub> < V<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>5<\/sub>","KMnO<sub>4<\/sub> < K<sub>2<\/sub>Cr<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>7<\/sub> < V<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>5<\/sub>","KMnO<sub>4<\/sub> < V<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>5<\/sub> < K<sub>2<\/sub>Cr<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>7<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>What is observed when aqueous solutions of each of tetraoxosulphate (VI) acid, potassium trioxoiodate (V) and potassium iodide are mixed together?<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["a white precipitate is formed","a green precipitate is formed","the mixture remains colourless","the mixture turns reddish brown"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>The solubility product of Cu(IO<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>2<\/sub> is 1.08 x 10<sup>-7<\/sup>. Assuming that neither ions react appreciably with water to form H<sup>+<\/sup> and OH<sup>-<\/sup>, what is the solubility of the salt?<\/b><\/p>","options":["2.7 x 10<sup>-8<\/sup> mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>","9.0 x 10<sup>-8<\/sup> mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>","3.0 x 10<sup>-3<\/sup> mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>","9.0 x 10<sup>-3<\/sup> mol dm<sup>-3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>2SO<sub>2(g)<\/sub> + O2<sub>(g)<\/sub> 2SO<sub>3(g)<\/sub>.\r\n<\/b><\/p><p><b>In the chemical reaction above, the substance that will increase the rate of production of sulphur (VI) oxide is<\/b><\/p>","options":["manganese (VI) oxide","finely divided iron","vanadium (V) oxide","nickel"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>What quantity of electricity will liberate 0.125 mole of oxygen molecules during the electrolysis of dilute sodium chloride solution? [F = 96500 Cmol<sup>-1<\/sup>]<\/b><\/p>","options":["24 125 coulombs","48 250 coulombs","72 375 coulombs","96 500 coulombs"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>When a current I was passed through an electrolyte solution for 40 minutes, a mass Xg of a univalent metal was deposited at the cathode. What mass of the metal will be deposited when a current 2I is passed through the solution for 10 minutes?<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["<sup>X<\/sup>\/<sub>4<\/sub> g","<sup>X<\/sup>\/<sub>2<\/sub> g","2X g","4X g"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Which of the following statements is true of the electrochemical series?<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["electropositivity of metals increase down the series","electropositivity of non-metals decrease down the series","electronegativity of non-metals decrease down the series","electropositivity of metals decrease down the series"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Chlorine, Bromine and Iodine resemble one another in the way they<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["dissolve in alkalis","react violently with hydrogen without heating","are liquids","displace one another from solutions of their salts"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>A pair of compounds that can be used to generate a gas which has physiological effect on human beings is<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["sodium trioxonitrate (V) and calcium chloride","sodium dioxonitrate (III) and ammonium chloride","sodium trioxonitrate (V) and ammonium chloride","sodium dioxonitrate (III) and potassium chloride"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>What properties of Duralumin makes it more useful than its constituent metals?<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["it is heavy with a high melting point","it is malleable and has high density","it is strong and light","it is hard and ductile"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>A metal that can be extracted from cassiterite is<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["calcium","magnesium","tin","copper"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>The hydrocarbon that burns in air with a sooty flame is<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>6<\/sub>","C<sub>3<\/sub>H<sub>8<\/sub>","C<sub>4<\/sub>H<sub>10<\/sub>","C<sub>6<\/sub>H<sub>6<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Which of the following is a solvent for perfumes?<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["C<sub>5<\/sub>H<sub>12<\/sub>","C<sub>4<\/sub>H<sub>6<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub>COOH","C<sub>2<\/sub>H<sub>5<\/sub>OH"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>An eruption polluted an environment with a gas suspected to be H<sub>2<\/sub>S, a poisonous gas. A rescue team should spray the environment with<\/b><\/p>","options":["water","moist SO<sub>2<\/sub>","acidified KMnO<sub>4<\/sub> and water","water, acidified KMnO<sub>4<\/sub> and oxygen"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>1.34g of hydrated sodium tetraoxosulphate (vi) was heated to give an anhydrous salt weighing 0.71g. The formula of the hydrated salt is ___. [Na = 23, S = 32, O=16 H = 1].<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["Na<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>.3H<sub>2<\/sub>O","Na<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>.7H<sub>2<\/sub>O","Na<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>.2H<sub>2<\/sub>O","Na<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>.H<sub>2<\/sub>O"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>The ion that may be assumed to have negligible concentration in a sample of water that lathers readily with soap is ___.<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["Mg<sup>2+<\/sup>","K<sup>+<\/sup>","Co<sub>3<\/sub><sup>2+<\/sup>","HCO<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>A substance S is isomorphous with another substance R. When a tiny crystal of S is added into a supersaturated solution of R.<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["S dissolves in the solution","crystals of R are precipitated","there is no observable change","R and S react to generate heat"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Which of the following dilute solutions has the lowest Ph value?<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["calcium trioxocarbonate (iv)","hydrochloric acid","ethanoic acid","all of the above"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Which of the following is a basic salt?<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["Na<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>3<\/sub>","Mg(OH)Cl","NaHCO<sub>3<\/sub>","K<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub>.Al(SO<sub>4<\/sub>)<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Which of the following acts as both reducing and oxidizing agent?<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["H<sub>2<\/sub>","SO<sub>2<\/sub>","H<sub>2<\/sub>S","CO<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Which of the following is neutral to litmus paper?<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["NH<sub>4<\/sub>Cl","Na<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>3<\/sub>","FeCl<sub>3<\/sub>","NaCl"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Bronze is an alloy of ___.<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["copper and zinc","copper and carbon","copper and tin","zinc and tin"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Polyvinyl chloride is used to produce<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["bread","pencils","ink","pipes"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>When two end alkyl groups of ethyl ethanoate are interchanged, the compound formed is known as<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["methyl ethanoate","ethyl propanoate","methyl propanoate","propyl ethanoate"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Phosphorus is stored underwater to prevent it from<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["dehydrating","becoming inert","smelling","catching fire"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>The chemical used for coagulating in water purification is<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["aluminum tetraoxosulphate (VI)","copper tetraoxosulphate (VI)","sodium tetraoxosulphate (IV)","calcium tetraoxosulphate (IV)"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>What is the decrease in volume of air when pyrogallol is shaken with 30.00cm<sup>3<\/sup> of air?<\/b><\/p>","options":["15.00cm<sup>3<\/sup>","6.30cm<sup>3<\/sup>","0.63cm<sup>3<\/sup>","0.06cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Deliquescent substance are used for<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["cooling","wetting","melting","drying"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Which of the following statements is correct about the average kinetic energy of the molecules of a gas?<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["it increase with increase in pressure","it increase at constant temperature","it increase with increase in temperature","it increase with increase in volume"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Four elements W, X, Y and Z have atomic number 2, 6, 16 and 20 respectively. Which of these elements is a metal?<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["X","W","Z","Y"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>An oxide XO<sub>2<\/sub> has a vapour density of 32. What is the atomic mass of X?<\/b><\/p>","options":["32","20","14","12"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>A particle that contains 9 protons, 10 neutrons and 10 electrons is a<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["negative ion","positive ion","neutral atom of non-metal","neutral atom of metal"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>25cm<sup>3<\/sup> of a gas X contains Z molecules at 15\u00b0C and 75mmHg. How many molecules will 25cm<sup>3<\/sup> of another gas Y contain at the same temperature and pressure?<\/b><\/p>","options":["2 Y","2 Z","Z","Y"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Alkanones are generally obtained by the oxidation of<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["primary alkanols","secondary alkanols","tertiary alkanols","alkanoic acid"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>The chlorinated alkane often used industrially to remove grease is<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["tetrachloromethane","chloromethane","trichloromethane","dichloromethane"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Unsaturated organic compounds are identified by decolourization of<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["silver bromine and potassium tetraoxomanganate (VII) solutions","bromine water and acidified potassium tetraoxomanganate (VII) solution","silver bromide solution and alkaline potassium","bromine water and alkaline potassium tetraoxomanganate solution (VII)"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>The least easily oxidized of the metals below is<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["Ca","Na","Zn","Al"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>A common characteristics of copper and silver in their usage as coinage metals is that they<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["have high metallic lustre","are not easily oxidized","are easily oxidized","are not easily reduced"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Synthesis gas a mixture of<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["CH<sub>4<\/sub> and H<sub>2<\/sub>O","CH<sub>4<\/sub> and H<sub>2<\/sub>","CO<sub>2<\/sub>","CO and H<sub>2<\/sub>O"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>The refreshing and characteristic taste of soda water and other soft drinks is as a result of the presence in them of<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["carbon(IV)oxide","carbon(II)oxide","soda","glucose"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>The substance often used for vulcanization of rubber is<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["chlorine","hydrogen peroxide","sulphur","tetraoxosulphate(IV)acid"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>For a reaction in equilibrium, the species involved in the equilibrium constant expression are<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["gaseous and solid species","liquid and solid species","solid and dissolved species","gaseous and dissolved species"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Powdered marble reacts faster with hydrochloric acid solution than the granular form because the powdered form has<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["more molecules","more atoms","larger surface area","relatively large mass"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Given that M is the mass of substance deposited in an electrolysis and Q the quantity of electricity consumed, then Faraday\u2019s law can be written as<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["M = Z\/Q","M = Q\/Z","M = Z\/2Q","M = QZ"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>MnO<sup>-<\/sup><sub>4(aq)<\/sub> + 8H<sup>+<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub> + Y \u279d Mn<sup>2+<\/sup><sub>(aq)<\/sub> + 4H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(l)<\/sub> Y in the equation above represents<\/b><\/p>","options":["2e<sup>-<\/sup>","3e<sup>-<\/sup>","5e<sup>-<\/sup>","7e<sup>-<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>In which order are the following salts sensitive to light?<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["Agl > AgCl > AgBr","AgCl > Agl > AgBr","AgBr > AgCl > Agl","AgCl > AgBr > Agl"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>Hydration of ions solutions is associated with<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["absorption of heat","reduction of heat","conduction of heat","liberation of heat"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>The air pollutant unknown in nature is<\/b><br><\/p>","options":["NO","CO","HCHO","DDT"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><b>A side effect of soft water is that<br><\/b><\/p>","options":["it gives offensive taste","excess calcium is precipitated","it attacks lead contained in pipes","it encourages the growth of bacteria"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"null"},{"question":"<p><strong>200 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of air was passed over heated copper in a syringe several times to produce copper (II)&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>oxide. When cooled, the final volume of air recorded was 158 cm<sup>3<\/sup>. Estimate the percentage of&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>oxygen in the air.<\/strong><\/p>","options":["31%","27%","21%","19%"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A mixture of sand, ammonium chloride and sodium chloride is best separated by __&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Sublimation followed by addition of water and filtration","Sublimation followed by addition of water and evaporation","Addition of water followed by filtration and sublimation","Addition of water followed by crystallization and sublimation"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>:CH<sub>4<\/sub> has this geometry:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Trigonal","Planar","Tetrahedral","Octahedral"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of these atomic shells is the most stable&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["M","N","K","L"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The number of atoms in one mole of a substance is equal to&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The atomic number","The Avogadro\u2019s number","Number of neutrons","Number of electrons"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The number of electrons in the outermost shell of the atom represents its <\/strong><\/p>","options":["Period","Number of shells","Group","Atomic number"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The partial pressure of oxygen in a sample of air is 500 mmHg. If the total Pr pressure 780 mmHg, what is the mole fraction of the oxygen?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["0.64","5.73","1.56","0.70"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The periodic classification of the elements is an arrangement of the elements in order of their<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Atomic weights","Isotopic weights","Molecular weights","Atomic numbers"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The shapes of CO<sub>2<\/sub>, H<sub>2<\/sub>O and CH<sub>4<\/sub> respectively are&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Bent, linear and tetrahedral","Bent, tetrahedral and linear","Tetrahedral, linear and bent","Linear, bent and tetrahedral"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>This compound exhibits ionic bonding&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["H20","H2","KCl","NH3"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which one of the following changes is physical?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Adding iron filings to aerated water","Adding sodium metal to water","Cooling a solution of iron(II)sulphate to obtain the hydrated salt","Cooling water to obtain ice"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><b>A side effect of soft water is that&nbsp;<\/b><\/p>","options":["It gives offensive taste","Excess calcium is precipitated","It encourages the growth of bacteria","It attacks lead contained in pipes"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Ammonia is very soluble in water because it is a \/an molecule&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Non-polar","Polar","Reactive","Basic"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Soap lather is an example of a colloid in which a&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Liquid is dispersed in gas","Solid is dispersed in liquid","Gas is dispersed in liquid","Liquid is dispersed in liquid"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The air around a petroleum refinery is most likely to contain.<\/strong><\/p>","options":["CO<sub>2<\/sub>, SO<sub>3<\/sub> and N<sub>2<\/sub>O","CO<sub>2<\/sub>, CO and N<sub>2<\/sub>O","SO<sub>2<\/sub>, CO and NO<sub>2<\/sub>","PH<sub>3<\/sub>, H<sub>2<\/sub>O and CO<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The difference between colloids and suspensions is brought out clearly by the fact that while&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>colloids<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Do not scatter light, suspensions do","Can be separated by filtration, suspensions cannot be so separated","Can be separated by a membrane, suspensions cannot","Do not settle out on standing, suspensions do"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The hydrolysis of NH<sub>4<\/sub>Cl salt will give&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Acidic solution","Neutral solution (C) basic solution (D) hot solution","Basic solution","Hot solution"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The pollutants that are likely to be present in an industrial environment are&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["H<sub>2<\/sub>S, SO<sub>2<\/sub> and oxides of nitrogen","NH<sub>3<\/sub>, HCl and CO","CO<sub>2<\/sub>, NH<sub>3<\/sub>, and H<sub>2<\/sub>S","Dust, NO and Cl<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>What is the basicity of tetraoxosulphate (VI) acid?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["2","1","3","4"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following ions is a pollutant in drinking water even in trace amount?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Ca<sup>2+<\/sup>","Hg<sup>2+<\/sup>","Mg<sup>2+<\/sup>","Fe<sup>2+<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is an example of a double salt&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["NH4Cl","Alum","NaCO3","AlCl3"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>0.16g of methane when burnt increases the temperature of 100g of water by 40<sup>0<\/sup>(C), what is&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>the heat of combustion of methane if the heat capacity of water is 4.2 Jg<sup>-1<\/sup>C<sup>-1<\/sup>? (CH<sub>4<\/sub>=16).<\/strong><\/p>","options":["1,160kJmol<sup>-1 <\/sup>","1,180kJmol<sup>-1 <\/sup>","1,560kJmol<sup>-1 <\/sup>","1,680kJmol<sup>-1 <\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A charged car battery has ___ energy that can be converted into another energy called ___energy<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Chemical, electrical","Mechanical, chemical","Heat, mechanical","Light, electrical"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>For each oxygen atom in hydrogen peroxide which acts as an oxidant, there is an oxygen atom&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>which acts as a \/an<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Oxidant","Reductant","Oxidizing agent","Catalyst"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Given the change of phase: CO<sub>2<\/sub>(g) changes to CO<sub>2<\/sub>(s), the entropy of the system&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Decreases","Increases","Remains the same","Remains mutual"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In which of the following is the entropy change positive?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Reaction between an acid and a base","Addition of concentrated acid to water.","Dissolution of sodium metal in water","Thermal dissociation of ammonium chloride."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of these elements is the best reducing agent.&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Pb","Rb","Al","In"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The name of the gas driven off at the negative electrode during the electrolysis of brine is ___<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Hydrogen","Chlorine","Oxygen","Sodium"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The oxidation state of P in H<sub>2<\/sub>P<sub>2<\/sub>0<sub>7<\/sub><sup>2-<\/sup> is ___&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["-3","+3","+1","+5"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The oxidation state of S in Ca(HS0<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>2<\/sub> is&nbsp; <u>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;<\/u><\/strong><\/p>","options":["+2","-2","+4","-4"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The oxidizing agent in the reaction, 3Br<sub>2<\/sub> + 6OH<sup>-<\/sup>&nbsp; \u2192&nbsp; BrO<sub>3<\/sub><sup>-<\/sup> + 5Br<sup>-<\/sup> + 3H<sub>2<\/sub>O is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Br<sub>2<\/sub>","OH<sup>-<\/sup>","BrO<sub>3<\/sub><sup>-<\/sup>","e<sup>-<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>When heat is absorbed during a chemical reaction, the reaction is said to be ___<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Thermodynamic","Exothermal","Isothermal","Endothermic"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Given the reaction at equilibrium: N<sub>2<\/sub>(g) + O<sub>2<\/sub>(g) &harr; 2NO(g) as the concentration of N<sub>2<\/sub>(g)&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>increases, the concentration of O<sub>2<\/sub>(g) will<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Decrease","Increase","Remains the same","Vanishes"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>If a reaction is exothermic and there is a great disorder, it means that&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The reaction is in a state of equilibrium","There will be a large increase in free energy","There will be a large decrease in free energy","The reaction is static."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In the chemical reaction of A + B = C +D, more of D is formed&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["If the concentration of A is reduced","If the concentration of B is reduced","If the concentration of C is reduced","If it is continuously removed from the reaction mixture"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In what way is equilibrium constant for the forward reaction related to that of the reverse&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>reaction?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The addition of the two is expected to be one.","The product of two is expected to be one.","The two equilibrium constants are identical.","The product of the two is always greater than one."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In which reaction will the point of equilibrium shift to the left when the pressure on the system&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>is increased?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["C(s) + O<sub>2<\/sub>(g) ? CO<sub>2<\/sub>(g)","CaCO<sub>3<\/sub>(s) ? CaO(s) + CO<sub>2<\/sub>(g)","2Mg(s) + O<sub>2<\/sub>(g) ? 2MgO(s)","2H<sub>2<\/sub>(g) + O<sub>2<\/sub>(g) ?2H2<sub>2<\/sub>(g)"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which is a property of a reaction that has reached equilibrium?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The amount of products is greater than the amount of reactants.","The amount of products is equal to the amount of reactants.","The rate of the forward reaction is greater than the rate of the reverse reaction.","The rate of the forward reaction is equal to the rate of the reverse reaction."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following combination of conditions many increase the rate of a chemical&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>reaction.<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Decrease in temperature, increase in concentration of the reactant","Increase in temperature, addition of a catalyst, decrease in the surface area of the reactant","Increase in temperature, increase in concentration, addition of a catalyst and increase in the surface area of the reactant","Decrease in temperature, concentration and surface area of the reactants"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Liquid oxygen may be produced by condensation of air using this coolant&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Liquid phosphorus","Liquid gas","Liquid paraffin","Liquid nitrogen"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Chlorine is produced commercially by&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Electrolysis of dilute HCl","Electrolysis of brine","Neutralization of HCI","Heating potassium trioxochlorate (V)"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Liquid oxygen may be produced by condensation of air using this coolant&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["liquid phosphorus","liquid gas","liquid paraffin","liquid nitrogen"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of these metals is not an alkali metal&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["K","Cs","Sr","Fr"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of these reactions represents the laboratory preparation of hydrogen.<\/strong><\/p>","options":["C<sub>(s)<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(l)<\/sub> \u2192 CO<sub>(g)<\/sub> + H<sub>2(g)<\/sub>","2 Na<sub>(s)<\/sub> + 2H<sub>2<\/sub>0<sub>(l)<\/sub> \u2192 2 NaOH<sub>(aq)<\/sub> + H<sub>2(g)<\/sub>","Cu<sub>(s)<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>(l)<\/sub> \u2192 CuO<sub>(s)<\/sub> + H<sub>2(g)<\/sub>","Zn<sub>(s)<\/sub> + 2HCl<sub>(aq)<\/sub> \u2192 ZnCl<sub>2(aq)<\/sub> + H<sub>2(g)<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The formation of ozone by reaction of O<sub>2<\/sub> with atomic oxygen in UV light occurs in&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Upper atmosphere","Inner atmosphere","Strastosphere","Hemisphere"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The halogen which is chiefly produced commercially from sea water is ___&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Fluorine","Chlorine","Bromine","Iodine"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The most stable allotropic form of sulphur at normal conditions is ___&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Monoclinic sulphur","Rhombic  sulphur","Amorphous sulphur","Plastic sulphur"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The products obtained when the following chemical reaction is completed and balanced&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>are&hellip;HNO<sub>3<\/sub> + Ca(OH)<sub>2<\/sub> &rarr; ______<\/strong><\/p>","options":["CaNO<sub>3<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O","Ca(NO3)<sub>2<\/sub> + 2 H<sub>2<\/sub>O","CaO + 2 NO<sub>2<\/sub> + 3H<sub>2<\/sub>O","Ca + 2 NO<sub>2<\/sub> + 2 H<sub>2<\/sub>O"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>What is the role of iron and Aluminium oxide in ammonia production?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Dehydrating agent","Catalytic agent","Oxidizing agent","Bonding agent"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is not an allotrope of carbon?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Diamond","Graphite","Buck ministerfullerene","None of the above"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which oxide is amphiprotic (amphoteric)?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["MgO","NaO","CaO","ZnO"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Alkanoic acids are weak acids and ionises in solution to give:&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["(A) R<sub>+<\/sup> + COOH","RCOO- + H<sup>+<\/sup>","RCOO<sup>+<\/sup> + H-","RCORCO+ + OH- + OH-"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>An excess of ethanol heated with concentrated H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> at a temperature of 180<sup>o<\/sup>C is dehydrated&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>to give mostly<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Ethane","Ethene","Ethanol","Ethoxyethane"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Butene can be distinguished from benzene by reaction with:&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Hydrochloric acid","Bromine water","Potassium sulphate","Sodium hydroxide"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In the manufacture of soap industrially, brine is used to.__________.the acid salt.&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Oxidise","Reduce","Bleach","Precipitate"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Potasium ethanoate is formed when:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Methanoic acid reacts with KOH","Ethanoic acid reacts with KOH","Methanol reacts with KCO3","Ethanol reacts with CH3COOH"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>What is the process associated with conversion of vegetable oil to soap?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Esterification","Saponification","Hydrolysis","Acidification"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>When ethanal vapour is passed over manganese (II) ethanoate (manganese acetate) catalyst in&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>the presence of air, the product is:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Ethanoate","Ethanol","Methanol","Ethanoic acid"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>When KOH is used instead of NaOH in the production of soap, it has the following advantages&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>except it gives:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Softer soap","Harder soap","Soap with lower melting point","More soluble soap"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p>&nbsp;<\/p>\r\n<p><strong>When palm wine is left exposed to air for a few days, it goes sour. The bacteria in the air&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>oxidises.________ in palm wine to _________<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Ethanol, ethanoic acid","Ethanoic acid, ethanol","Ester, ethanoic acid","Ether, ethanol"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is not true about benzoic acid? <\/strong><\/p>","options":["It is aromatic in nature","It can be manufactured from methylbenzene","It has molecular formula C6H6COOH","It sublimes readily"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is not true about benzoic acid?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["It is aromatic in nature","It can be manufactured from methylbenzene","It has molecular formula C<sub>6<\/sub>H<sub>6<\/sub>COOH","It sublimes readily"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of these is not a property of ethanedioic acid?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["It is a stronger acid than ethanoic acid but weaker than inorganic acids","It is a reducing agent","It is an oxidising agent","It is soluble in cold water"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"}]